Finding Aid for Ronald Lippitt Papers 1938-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ronald Lippitt Papers 1938-1987, 1974-1986
Lippitt, Ronald.
7 linear feet
Professor of psychology and sociology at the University of Michigan, one of the founders of Center for Research on the Utilization of Scientific Knowledge. Through his writings, workshops, and consultation work, Lippitt was advocate for use of behavioral science to improve the quality of service and productivity within organizations. Lippitt wrote on such topics as group dynamics, futuring, processes of learning, socialization, and growth of children and youth. The collection relates primarily to Lippit's activities since retiring from the University of Michigan in 1974. The bulk of the collection consists of writings and publications, organizational materials, and a selection of files from the workshops and seminars given by Lippitt and his associates.
0081 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was accessioned in January of 2000. Donor no. 8917.
The collection is open for research.
Born and raised in Minnesota, Ronald Lippitt began what was to become a long and prolific career in social psychology at Springfield College in Massachusetts, where he received undergraduate and professional training in group work and received his B.S. Lippitt spent his junior year of college abroad on a Foreign Study Scholarship, studying under Jean Piaget at the Rousseau Institute at the University of Geneva, from which he received a Certificat de Pedagogie in Child Development in 1935. Lippitt then received his M.A. in Child Development (1938) and Ph.D. in Social Psychology (1940) from the University of Iowa, where he studied under Kurt Lewin. Lippitt assisted Lewin in his studies of the effects of authoritarian, democratic, and laissez-faire group leadership on group process and productivity in after-school boys social clubs. This work subsequently led to their co-founding of the field of group dynamics.
Upon receiving his Ph.D. in 1940, Lippitt taught as assistant professor of psychology at Southern Illinois University from 1940 to 1941. From 1941 through 1944 Lippitt was director of research for the National Council of Boy Scouts, where he developed a national study of the impact of leadership styles on character development climates. With the onset of World War II, he became an officer in the Commissioned Corps of the Public Health Service, conducting group therapy sessions for the navy. Lippitt then directed the Far East Psychological Warfare Training School for the Office of Strategic Services, with a multi-disciplinary staff including anthropologists Margaret Mead and Ruth Benedict, media, intelligence specialists, and Japanese and Chinese psychiatrists. When the war ended, Lippitt became director of training for the Federal Security Agency. There he co-led with Leland Bradford a program of organization change intervention by a multiple entry strategy, in federal agencies and hospitals.
In 1946 Lippitt resumed work with Kurt Lewin, helping him to found the Research Center for Group Dynamics at M.I.T., where Lippitt was also an associate professor of social science from 1946 to 1948. In 1947 Lippitt, Lewin, Leland Bradford and Kenneth Benne co-founded the National Training Laboratories for Applied Behavioral Science (NTL) and invented the T-group (Basic Skill Training Group), or "Sensitivity Training" at Bethel, Maine, which was the first instance of laboratory training for organizational development. Upon Lewin's death in 1948, Lippitt moved the Research Center for Group Dynamics to the University of Michigan's Institute of Social Research, acting as program director in the Research Center, as well as associate professor of sociology and psychology at the university. Lippitt became full professor of sociology and psychology in 1952. In 1964, dissatisfied with the emphasis on pure research without concern for its utility, Lippitt founded, along with Floyd Mann, the Center for Research on the Utilization of Social Knowledge (CRUSK) as a part of the Institute of Social Research. This was a laboratory of planned change which became a training and consultation organization, drawing clients from the surrounding community.
In 1974 Lippitt retired as professor emeritus of psychology and sociology from the University of Michigan, in order to focus on assisting private and public sector systems in the use of behavioral science to improve the quality of service and productivity. In the following years he founded and participated in several organizations offering management and planned change consultation, including Human Resource Development Associates with Ken Cowing and Della Cowing; Hilltop Associates with Eva Schindler-Rainman; Organization Renewal, Inc. (ORI), with his brother Gordon Lippitt; Planned Change Associates, Inc.(PCA); and Xicom, Inc. Lippitt also ran a group in his home referred to as Lippitt and Associates or the Lippitt Cluster, in which once a month friends and colleagues met to share ideas, goals, and interactions. In conjunction with these organizations Lippitt conducted numerous workshops and training programs in the United States and abroad.
Throughout his academic and professional career, Lippitt published extensively, both individually and jointly with colleagues such as Eva Schindler-Rainman, with whom he frequently worked on projects concerning community organization and volunteerism. Lippitt is the author or co-author of over 200 articles and books, on such topics as group dynamics, futuring, the processes of learning, socialization and growth of children and youth, leadership, planned change and change agentry, community planning, and renewal and reconstruction of the traditional educational system and practices. (A complete bibliography is located in Box 1.)
A member of several professional societies, Lippitt was a fellow in the International Association of Applied Social Scientists, the Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues, the Association of Voluntary Action Scholars, the Clinical Sociology Association, and the American Psychological Association, in addition to serving on the editorial board of the Clinical Sociology Review. Honors Lippitt received during his career include the Distinguished Career Award of the Clinical Sociology Association in 1985, a Concurrent Resolution of Tribute from the Michigan Legislature in 1984, and honorary doctorates from Springfield College, in 1962, and Leslie College, in 1965.
Lippitt died October 28, 1986, at the age of 72, and was survived by his wife, Peggy Lippitt, son Larry Lippitt, daughters Martha Lippitt, Carolyn McCarthy and Connie Cohn, and nine grandchildren.
The papers of Ronald O. Lippitt chiefly document Lippitt's activities following his retirement from the University of Michigan. The bulk of the collection consists of materials pertaining to several of the consulting organizations of which he was a part, and workshops and programs which he led for national and local organizations, schools and communities. The collection also offers a substantial run of Lippitt's writings and publications, from his entire scholarly and professional career. The papers have been arranged into five series: Biographical/ Personal (1946-1986); University of Michigan (1967-1975); Organizations (1974-1987); Workshops (1969-1986); and Writings and Publications (1938-1986).
Subjects:
Behaviorism (Psychology); Business consultants.; Community development.; Community organization.; Lippitt, Ronald.; Lippitt and Associates.; NTL Institute for Applied Behavior Science.; Organization Renewal, Inc.; Organizational change.; Planned Change Associates.; Problem solving.; Psychology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Xicom.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Lippitt, Ronald.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/ Personal
  The Biographical/ Personal series spans .25 linear feet, and includes material such as articles written about Lippitt and his work at various stages of his career, biographical sketches, transcripts of interviews with Lippitt (including one with he and Eva Schindler-Rainman), curriculum vitae, and a complete bibliography of Lippitt's publications compiled by Lippitt in 1986. This series also contains one folder of photographs of Lippitt at various times in his life, including one of Lippitt in 1932, several taken at the time of his retirement, and many taken at various workshops or programs during the following years. This series also contains one folder of correspondence with family and colleagues. Additional correspondence relating to particular organizations, workshops, or publications is located throughout the collection.
  - Articles about Lippitt 1946-1986 (Box 1)
  - Award certificates 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Bibliography 1986 (Box 1)
  - Biographical sketches, created 1975-1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1974-1986 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum vitae (Box 1)
  - Interviews 1977-1985 (Box 1)
  - Last Will and Testaments, Ronald and Peggy Lippitt 1978 (Box 1)
  - Lippitt, Gordon, Curriculum vita (Box 1)
  - Lippitt, Lawrence, Curriculum vita (Box 1)
  - Lippitt, Mary Burner, Curriculum vita (Box 1)
  - Lippitt, Peggy, Curriculum vita (Box 1)
  - Memorial Service and Remembrances 1986 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries 1986 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Schedules 1981-1983 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series spans .1 linear feet, and includes documents outlining the terms and conditions of Lippitt's appointments, syllabi and course materials for two courses taught by Lippitt at the university, and the statement written for publication in the Regents Proceedings announcing Lippitt's retirement.
  - Appointment, terms and conditions 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Course Syllabi, Psych-Soc 685/686 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Retirement notice 1975 (Box 1)
- Organizations
  The Organizations series spans 1 linear foot and includes materials pertaining to five organizations in which Lippitt participated in the years following his retirement from the university: Lippitt and Associates/Lippitt Cluster; NTL Institute for Applied Behavioral Science; Organization Renewal, Inc. (ORI); Planned Change Associates (PCA); and Xicom, Inc. Among these materials are membership and personnel listings, meeting minutes and materials, correspondence, brochures, and materials pertaining to workshops and programs given by these organizations.
  - Lippitt and Associates/ Lippitt Cluster 1980-1987
    - Membership Directories 1981, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes and Materials
      - 1980-1982 (Box 1)
      - 1983 (Box 1)
      - 1984 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - National Training Laboratories (NTL) Institute for Applied Behavioral Science 1975-1986
    - Board of Directors/ Executive Board Meeting Materials
      - 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Brochures (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda
      - 1978-1980 (Box 1)
      - 1981 (Box 1)
      - 1982-1986 (Box 1)
    - Membership 1975-1981 (Box 1)
    - "News and Views" Newsletter 1981-1985 (Box 1)
    - Policy, By-laws, and Ethics 1978-1982 (Box 1)
    - Research and Development 1982-1985 (Box 1)
    - Workshop Materials 1979-1988
      - Participant and Staff Listings 1980 (Box 1)
      - Futuring 1981-1986 (Box 1)
      - Integrated Training and Consultation (ITC) 1980-1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Intervention Skillshop (ISK) 1979-1986 (Box 1)
  - Organization Renewal, Inc. (ORI) 1980-1986
    - Antioch University Contract 1984 (Box 2)
    - Application and Contractual Agreement Forms (Box 2)
    - Brochures (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1980-1986 (Box 2)
    - Financial 1983-1985 (Box 2)
    - Meeting Materials 1984-1986, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Personnel (Box 2)
    - Policy, By-laws, and Ethics (Box 2)
    - Stock Certificate 1980 (Box 2)
  - Planned Change Associates (PCA) 1984-1986
    - Brochures (Box 2)
    - Bylaws (Box 2)
    - Community Interviews 1985 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - Financial 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - Meeting Minutes 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Xicom, Inc
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1974-1978 (Box 2)
    - Meetings and Financial 1972-1976 (Box 2)
    - Personnel, photographs and curriculum vitae (Box 2)
    - Workshop notices and materials 1973-1977 (Box 2)
- Workshops
  The Workshops series spans 1.25 linear feet and is comprised of a representative sampling of the types of workshops Lippitt conducted or co-conducted over the years. These materials are arranged chronologically by year and, within each year, listed by title of the event. Researchers should note that the workshops included here reflect only a very small number of those which Lippitt participated in. They were selected because they offer a good amount of material reflecting the processes involved, and often include handouts and other materials, participant lists, Lippitt's notes, workshop evaluations, and summaries of what was accomplished or produced as a result of the workshop. These workshops were conducted under the auspices of the different organizations with which Lippitt was involved since 1974.
  - 1969
    - Girl Scout Convention Collaboration (Box 2)
    - National YMCA Leadership Consultation (Box 2)
  - 1971
    - Lutheran Social Services Conference (Box 2)
    - National Inter-agency Consultation on Youth (Box 2)
    - Westchester Volunteer Service Bureau Forum (Box 2)
  - 1972
    - Los Angeles City School Volunteer Program (Box 2)
  - 1973
    - Consulting Skills, Philadelphia, PA (Box 2)
    - Human Resource Development Associates Professional Development (Box 2)
  - 1974
    - Oakland University, "Images of Potentiality" (Box 2)
    - Reading Specialists of Michigan (Box 2)
  - 1975
    - Los Angeles united School District Compensatory Education (Box 2)
  - 1976
    - Lake Arrowhead Conference for Administrators and Directors of Volunteer Programs (Box 2)
    - Open University (Box 2)
    - New York University, Strategies and Techniques of Planned Change (Box 2)
  - 1977
    - USAREUR Recreation Centers, Nuremberg, Germany (Box 2)
    - Health Occupations Educators Workshop (Box 2)
    - Lake Arrowhead Conference for Administrators and Directors of Volunteer Programs (Box 2)
  - 1978
    - Kean College of New Jersey, Department of Special Education and Individualized Services (Box 2)
    - Girl Scouts of America Trainers of Trainers Workshop (Box 2)
    - Communication Fair, Duluth, MN (Box 2)
  - 1979
    - Human Resource Development Associates, Designing Participative Learning Experiences (Box 3)
    - International Conference on the Future of Public Administration, Quebec, Canada (Box 3)
    - YMCA National Goals Steering Committee (Box 3)
  - 1980
    - Eastern Michigan University College of Business Renewal Project (Box 3)
    - Michigan Union Staff Workshop (Box 3)
    - Ypsilanti Area Futures Project (Box 3)
  - 1982
    - University of Michigan Hospital Directors Executive Council (Box 3)
    - Jackson Community College (Box 3)
    - Bell Laboratories (Box 3)
  - 1983
    - Planned Change in the 80's (Box 3)
    - Quality Management in the Hospital, Hilton Head Island, SC (Box 3)
  - 1984
    - Ford Motor Co (Box 3)
    - Jackson County, Futuring (Box 3)
  - 1985
    - Mercy Medical Center Retreat, "Resizing via Futuring" (Box 3)
    - Lear Siegler, Inc (Box 3)
  - 1986
    - Pillsbury Learning Center (Box 3)
    - Integrating Eastern and Western Wisdom for O. D. Practice (Box 3)
- Writings and Publications
  The final series, Writings and Publications, spans 4.5 linear feet and includes drafts or reprints of articles, books, research reports, and other writings authored or co-authored by Lippitt. The series is first arranged chronologically; among other writings included are drafts of three books: Building the Collaborative Community (1980), The Consulting Process in Action (1985), and The Multocular Process (1985, including original paper dated 1975 and publication correspondence). Following the chronological arrangement is one folder of articles and writings of Rosemary Lippitt, Lippitt's first wife, who conducted work on the subject of children and Role-Playing before her death in 1958. There then follows one folder of articles and writings of Peggy Lippitt, who conducted research into cross-age helping programs. It should be noted that several articles co-authored by Ronald and Peggy Lippitt are included in the chronological arrangement. Finally, the series includes several kits or programs including printed and audio materials: "Cross-Age Helping Program," "Developing Our Volunteer Community," "The Flint Youth Study Experience," and "Reality Practice: Methods and Theory of Role-Playing."
  - Chronological
    - 1938-1944 (Box 3)
    - 1944-1947 (Box 3)
    - 1948-1950 (Box 3)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 4)
    - 1955-1957 (Box 4)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 4)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 4)
    - 1963 (Box 4)
    - 1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1965 (Box 4)
    - 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1967, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1968, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1969, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 5)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - 1975 (Box 5)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - 1980, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1981 (Box 6)
    - 1982 (Box 6)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 6)
    - 1985, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 1986 (Box 6)
    - Undated (Box 6)
  - Others
    - Rosemary Lippitt 1941-1958 (Box 6)
    - Peggy Lippitt, 1961-197? (Box 6)
  - Programs and Kits
    - Cross-Age Helping Program (Box 7)
      includes two 12" sound discs
    - Developing Our Volunteer Community (Box 7)
      includes 4 audio cassettes
    - The Flint Youth Study Experience (Box 7)
      includes 7 10" sound discs
    - Reality Practice: Methods and Theory of Role-Playing (Box 7)
      includes 3 audio cassettes